<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/xsl/current/manpages/docbook.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<refentry xml:id="mosquitto.conf">
	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>mosquitto.conf</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
	</refmeta>

	<refnamediv>
		<refname>mosquitto.conf</refname>
		<refpurpose>the configuration file for mosquitto</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>

	<refsynopsisdiv>
		<cmdsynopsis>
			<command>mosquitto.conf</command>
		</cmdsynopsis>
	</refsynopsisdiv>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Description</title>
		<para><command>mosquitto.conf</command> is the configuration file for
		mosquitto. This file can reside anywhere as long as mosquitto can read
		it. By default, mosquitto does not need a configuration file and will
		use the default values listed below. See
		<citerefentry><refentrytitle>mosquitto</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
		for information on how to load a configuration file.</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>File Format</title>
		<para>All lines with a # as the very first character are treated as a comment.</para>
		<para>Configuration lines start with a variable name. The variable value is separated from the name by a single space.</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Variables</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>autosave_interval</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The number of seconds that mosquitto will wait 
					between each time it saves the in-memory database to 
					disk. If set to 0, the in-memory database will only
					be saved when mosquitto exits or when receiving the 
					SIGUSR1 signal. Note that this setting only has an 
					effect if persistence is enabled.  Defaults to 1800 
					seconds (30 minutes).</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>ext_sqlite_regex</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The path to the sqlite3 regex extension which is
					needed for wildcard subscription matching. If it is not
					found, mosquitto will not start. The default when compiled
					for Windows is "./sqlite3-pcre.dll" and for other platforms
					"/usr/lib/sqlite3/pcre.so".</para>
					<para>The sqlite3 pcre extension used is available at
					http://git.altlinux.org/people/at/packages/?p=sqlite3-pcre.git</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>interface</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Listen for incoming network connections on the
					specified interface only. The port to listen to can be
					changed from the default by appending it to the interface
					name, e.g. eth0:1884. This is useful to restrict access to
					certain network interfaces. To restrict access to mosquitto
					to the local host only, use "interface lo". This option
					may be specified multiple times.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>log_dest</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Send log messages to a particular destination.
					Possible destinations are: stdout stderr syslog topic.
					stdout and stderr log to the console on the named output.
					syslog uses the userspace syslog facility which usually
					ends up in /var/log/messages or similar and topic logs to the
					broker topic '$SYS/broker/log/&lt;severity&gt;', where severity
					is one of D, E, W, N, I which are debug, error, warning,
					notice and information. Use "log_dest none" if you wish to
					disable logging. Defaults to stderr. This option
					may be specified multiple times.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>log_type</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Choose types of messages to log. Possible types are:
					debug, error, warning, notice, information, none. Defaults
					to error, warning, notice and information. This option may
					be specified multiple times. Note that the debug type (used
					for decoding incoming network packets) is never logged in
					syslog or topics.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>port</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the network port to listen on. Defaults to 1883. This option may be given any number of times. A socket will be created for each port listed.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>persistence</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Can be true or false. If true, connection, subscription and message data will be written to the disk in mosquitto.db at the location dictated by persistence_location. When mosquitto is restarted, it will reload the information stored in mosquitto.db. The data will be written to disk when mosquitto closes and also at periodic intervals as defined by autosave_interval. Writing of the persistence database may also be forced by sending mosquitto the SIGUSR1 signal. If false, the data will be stored in memory only. Defaults to false.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>persistence_location</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The path where the persistence database should be stored. Must end in a trailing slash. If not given, then the current directory is used.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>pid_file</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Write a pid file to the file specified. If not given
					(the default), no pid file will be written. If the pid file
					cannot be written, mosquitto will exit. This option only
					has an effect is mosquitto is run in daemon mode.</para>
					<para>If mosquitto is being automatically started by an
					init script it will usually be required to write a pid
					file. This should then be configured as
					/var/run/mosquitto.pid</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>retry_interval</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The integer number of seconds after a QoS=1 or QoS=2 message has been sent that mosquitto will wait before retrying when no response is received. If unset, defaults to 20 seconds.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>sys_interval</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The integer number of seconds between updates of the $SYS subscription hierarchy, which provides status information about the broker. If unset, defaults to 10 seconds.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>user</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>When run as root, change to this user and its primary
					group on startup.  If mosquitto is unable to change to this
					user and group, it will exit with an error. The user
					specified must have read/write access to the persistence
					database if it is to be written. If run as a non-root user,
					this setting has no effect. Defaults to mosquitto.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Files</title>
		<para>mosquitto.conf</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Bugs</title>
		<para><command>mosquitto</command> bug information can be found at <uri type="webpage">http://launchpad.net/mosquitto</uri>.</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>See Also</title>
		<para>
			<citerefentry>
				<refentrytitle>mosquitto</refentrytitle>
				<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
			</citerefentry>
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Author</title>
		<para>Roger Light <email>roger@atchoo.org</email></para>
	</refsect1>
</refentry>
