<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/xsl/current/manpages/docbook.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<refentry xml:id="mosquitto.conf">
	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>mosquitto.conf</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
	</refmeta>

	<refnamediv>
		<refname>mosquitto.conf</refname>
		<refpurpose>the configuration file for mosquitto</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>

	<refsynopsisdiv>
		<cmdsynopsis>
			<command>mosquitto.conf</command>
		</cmdsynopsis>
	</refsynopsisdiv>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Description</title>
		<para><command>mosquitto.conf</command> is the configuration file for
		mosquitto. This file can reside anywhere as long as mosquitto can read
		it. By default, mosquitto does not need a configuration file and will
		use the default values listed below. See
		<citerefentry><refentrytitle>mosquitto</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
		for information on how to load a configuration file.</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>File Format</title>
		<para>All lines with a # as the very first character are treated as a
		comment.</para>
		<para>Configuration lines start with a variable name. The variable
		value is separated from the name by a single space.</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Variables</title>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>acl_file</option> <replaceable>file path</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the path to an access control list file. If
					defined, the contents of the file are used to control
					client access to topics on the broker.</para>
					<para>If this parameter is defined then only the topics
					listed will have access. Topic access is added with lines
					of the format:</para>

					<para><code>topic [read|write] &lt;topic&gt;</code></para>

					<para>The access type is controlled using "read" or
					"write". This parameter is optional - if not given then the
					access is read/write.  &lt;topic&gt; can contain the + or #
					wildcards as in subscriptions.</para>

					<para>The first set of topics are applied to anonymous
					clients, assuming allow_anonymous is true. User specific
					topic ACLs are added after a user line as follows:</para>

					<para><code>user &lt;username&gt;</code></para>

					<para>The username referred to here is the same as in
					password_file. It is not the clientid.</para>

					<para>It is also possible to define ACLs based on pattern
					substitution within the topic. The form is the same as for
					the topic keyword, but using pattern as the keyword.</para>
					<para><code>pattern [read|write] &lt;topic&gt;</code></para>
					
					<para>The patterns available for substition are:</para>
					<itemizedlist mark="circle">
						<listitem><para>%c to match the client id of the client</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>%u to match the username of the client</para></listitem>
					<!-- BUG - putting itemizedlist close tag here breaks the
						 indentation of the man page. -->
					<para>The substitution pattern must be the only text for
					that level of hierarchy. Pattern ACLs apply to all users
					even if the "user" keyword has previously been
					given.</para>

					<para>Example:</para>
					<para><code>pattern write sensor/%u/data</code></para>

					<para>Reloaded on reload signal. The currently loaded ACLs will be
					freed and reloaded. Existing subscriptions will be affected
					after the reload.</para>

					<!-- BUG - this should be above. -->
					</itemizedlist>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>allow_anonymous</option> [ true | false ]</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Boolean value that determines whether clients that
					connect without providing a username are allowed to
					connect. If set to false then a password file should be
					created (see the password_file option) to control
					authenticated client access. Defaults to true.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>autosave_interval</option> <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The number of seconds that mosquitto will wait 
					between each time it saves the in-memory database to 
					disk. If set to 0, the in-memory database will only
					be saved when mosquitto exits or when receiving the 
					SIGUSR1 signal. Note that this setting only has an 
					effect if persistence is enabled.  Defaults to 1800 
					seconds (30 minutes).</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>bind_address</option> <replaceable>address</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Listen for incoming network connections on the
					specified IP address/hostname only. This is useful to
					restrict access to certain network interfaces. To restrict
					access to mosquitto to the local host only, use "bind_address
					localhost". This only applies to the default listener. Use
					the listener variable to control other listeners.</para>
					<para>Not reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>clientid_prefixes</option> <replaceable>prefix</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>If defined, only clients that have a clientid with a
					prefix that matches clientid_prefixes will be allowed to
					connect to the broker. For example, setting "secure-" here
					would mean a client "secure-client" could connect but
					another with clientid "mqtt" couldn't. By default, all
					client ids are valid.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal. Note that currently connected
					clients will be unaffected by any changes.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>listener</option> <replaceable>port</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Listen for incoming network connection on the
					specified port. A second optional argument allows the
					listener to be bound to a specific ip address/hostname. If
					this variable is used and neither bind_address nor port are
					used then the default listener will not be started. This
					option may be specified multiple times. See also the
					mount_point option.</para>
					<para>Not reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>log_dest</option> <replaceable>destinations</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Send log messages to a particular destination.
					Possible destinations are: stdout stderr syslog topic.
					stdout and stderr log to the console on the named output.
					syslog uses the userspace syslog facility which usually
					ends up in /var/log/messages or similar and topic logs to the
					broker topic '$SYS/broker/log/&lt;severity&gt;', where severity
					is one of D, E, W, N, I which are debug, error, warning,
					notice and information. Use "log_dest none" if you wish to
					disable logging. Defaults to stderr. This option
					may be specified multiple times.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>log_timestamp</option> [ true | false ]</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Boolean value, if set to true a timestamp value will
					be added to each log entry. The default is true.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>log_type</option> <replaceable>types</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Choose types of messages to log. Possible types are:
					debug, error, warning, notice, information, none. Defaults
					to error, warning, notice and information. This option may
					be specified multiple times. Note that the debug type (used
					for decoding incoming network packets) is never logged in
					syslog or topics.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>max_connections</option> <replaceable>count</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Limit the total number of clients connected for the
					current listener. Set to <literal>-1</literal> to have
					"unlimited" connections. Note that other limits may be
					imposed that are outside the control of mosquitto.  See
					e.g.
					<citerefentry><refentrytitle>limits.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>.</para>
					<para>Not reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>max_inflight_messages</option> <replaceable>count</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The maximum number of QoS 1 or 2 messages that can be
					in the process of being transmitted simultaneously.  This
					includes messages currently going through handshakes and
					messages that are being retried. Defaults to 20. Set to 0
					for no maximum. If set to 1, this will guarantee in-order
					delivery of messages.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>max_queued_messages</option> <replaceable>count</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The maximum number of QoS 1 or 2 messages to hold in
					the queue above those messages that are currently in
					flight. Defaults to 100. Set to 0 for no maximum (not
					recommended).</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>mount_point</option> <replaceable>topic prefix</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This option is used with the listener option to
					isolate groups of clients. When a client connects to a
					listener which uses this option, the string argument is
					attached to the start of all topics for this client. This
					prefix is removed when any messages are sent to the client.
					This means a client connected to a listener with mount
					point <option>example</option> can only see messages that
					are published in the topic hierarchy
					<option>example</option> and above.</para>
					<para>Not reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>password_file</option> <replaceable>file path</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the path to a password file. If defined, the
					contents of the file are used to control client access to
					the broker. Each line should be in the format
					"username:password", where the colon and password are
					optional but recommended. If allow_anonymous is set to
					false, only users defined in this file will be able to
					connect. Setting allow_anonymous to true when password_file
					is defined is valid and could be used with acl_file to have
					e.g. read only guest/anonymous accounts and defined users
					that can publish.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal. The currently loaded username and
					password data will be freed and reloaded. Clients that are
					already connected will not be affected.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>persistence</option> [ true | false ]</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Can be true or false. If true, connection,
					subscription and message data will be written to the disk
					in mosquitto.db at the location dictated by
					persistence_location. When mosquitto is restarted, it will
					reload the information stored in mosquitto.db. The data
					will be written to disk when mosquitto closes and also at
					periodic intervals as defined by autosave_interval. Writing
					of the persistence database may also be forced by sending
					mosquitto the SIGUSR1 signal. If false, the data will be
					stored in memory only. Defaults to false.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>persistence_file</option> <replaceable>file name</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The filename to use for the persistent database. Defaults to mosquitto.db.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>persistence_location</option> <replaceable>path</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The path where the persistence database should be
					stored. Must end in a trailing slash. If not given, then
					the current directory is used.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>pid_file</option> <replaceable>file path</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Write a pid file to the file specified. If not given
					(the default), no pid file will be written. If the pid file
					cannot be written, mosquitto will exit. This option only
					has an effect is mosquitto is run in daemon mode.</para>
					<para>If mosquitto is being automatically started by an
					init script it will usually be required to write a pid
					file. This should then be configured as
					/var/run/mosquitto.pid</para>
					<para>Not reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>port</option> <replaceable>port number</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the network port for the default listener to
					listen on. Defaults to 1883.</para>
					<para>Not reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>retained_persistence</option> [ true | false ]</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This is a synonym of the <option>persistence</option>
					option.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>retry_interval</option> <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The integer number of seconds after a QoS=1 or QoS=2
					message has been sent that mosquitto will wait before
					retrying when no response is received. If unset, defaults
					to 20 seconds.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>store_clean_interval</option> <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The integer number of seconds between the internal
					message store being cleaned of messages that are no longer
					referenced.  Lower values will result in lower memory usage
					but more processor time, higher values will have the
					opposite effect. Setting a value of 0 means the
					unreferenced messages will be disposed of as quickly as
					possible. Defaults to 10 seconds.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>sys_interval</option> <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The integer number of seconds between updates of the
					$SYS subscription hierarchy, which provides status
					information about the broker. If unset, defaults to 10
					seconds.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>user</option> <replaceable>username</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>When run as root, change to this user and its primary
					group on startup.  If mosquitto is unable to change to this
					user and group, it will exit with an error. The user
					specified must have read/write access to the persistence
					database if it is to be written. If run as a non-root user,
					this setting has no effect. Defaults to mosquitto.</para>
					<para>This setting has no effect on Windows and so you
					should run mosquitto as the user you wish it to run
					as.</para>
					<para>Not reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Configuring Bridges</title>
		<para>Multiple bridges (connections to other brokers) can be configured
		using the following variables.</para>
		<para>Bridges cannot currently be reloaded on reload signal.</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>address</option> <replaceable>address[:port]</replaceable></term>
				<term><option>addresses</option> <replaceable>address[:port]</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Specify the address and optionally the port of the
					bridge to connect to. This must be given for each bridge
					connection. If the port is not specified, the default of
					1883 is used.</para>
					<para>Unlike rsmb, it is not currently possible to specify
					multiple addresses for a single bridge connection
					here. This is true even if the name "addresses" is used.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>cleansession</option> [ true | false ]</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the clean session option for this bridge. Setting
					to false (the default), means that all subscriptions on the
					remote broker are kept in case of the network connection
					dropping. If set to true, all subscriptions and messages on
					the remote broker will be cleaned up if the connection
					drops. Note that setting to true may cause a large amount
					of retained messages to be sent each time the bridge
					reconnects.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>clientid</option> <replaceable>id</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the client id for this bridge connection. If not
					defined, this defaults to 'name.hostname', where name is
					the connection name and hostname is the hostname of this
					computer.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>connection</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This variable marks the start of a new bridge
					connection. It is also used to give the bridge a
					name which is used as the client id on the remote
					broker.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>keepalive_interval</option> <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the number of seconds after which the bridge
					should send a ping if no other traffic has occurred.
					Defaults to 60. A minimum value of 5 seconds
					isallowed.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>idle_timeout</option> <replaceable>seconds</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the amount of time a bridge using the lazy start
					type must be idle before it will be stopped. Defaults to
					60 seconds.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>notifications</option> [ true | false ]</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>If set to true, publish notification messages to the
					local and remote brokers giving information about the state
					of the bridge connection. Retained messages are published
					to the topic $SYS/bridge/connection/&lt;clientid&gt;/state.
					If the message is 1 then the connection is active, or 0 if
					the connection has failed. Defaults to true.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>password</option> <replaceable>value</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Configure a password for the bridge. This is used for
					authentication purposes when connecting to a broker that
					support MQTT v3.1 and requires a username and/or password
					to connect. This option is only valid if a username is also
					supplied.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>start_type</option> [ automatic | lazy | once ]</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the start type of the bridge. This controls how
					the bridge starts and can be one of three types: automatic,
					lazy and once. Note that RSMB provides a fourth start type
					"manual" which isn't currently supported by
					mosquitto.</para>

					<para>"automatic" is the default start type and means that
					the bridge connection will be started automatically when
					the broker starts and also restarted after a short delay
					(30 seconds) if the connection fails.</para>

					<para>Bridges using the "lazy" start type will be started
					automatically when the number of queued messages exceeds
					the number set with the "threshold" parameter. It will be
					stopped automatically after the time set by the
					"idle_timeout" parameter. Use this start type if you wish
					the connection to only be active when it is needed.</para>

					<para>A bridge using the "once" start type will be started
					automatically when the broker starts but will not be
					restarted if the connection fails.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>threshold</option> <replaceable>count</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set the number of messages that need to be queued
					for a bridge with lazy start type to be restarted.
					Defaults to 10 messages.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>topic</option> <replaceable>pattern</replaceable> [ out | in | both ]</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Define a topic pattern to be shared between the two
					brokers. Any topics matching the pattern (which may include
					wildcards) are shared. The second parameter defines the
					direction that the messages will be shared in, so it is
					possible to import messages from a remote broker using
					"in", export messages to a remote broker using "out" or
					share messages in both directions. If this parameter is not
					defined, the default of "out" is used.</para>
					<para>This option can be specified multiple times per
					bridge.</para>
					<para>Care must be taken to ensure that loops are not
					created with this option. If you are experiencing high CPU
					load from a broker, it is possible that you have a loop
					where each broker is forever forwarding each other the same
					messages.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>username</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Configure a username for the bridge. This is used for
					authentication purposes when connecting to a broker that
					support MQTT v3.1 and requires a username and/or password
					to connect. See also the password option.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>External Security Checks</title>
		<para>The following options are available when external security checks
		have been compiled in. Unless you have done this yourself it is
		unlikely to exist.</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>db_host</option> <replaceable>hostname</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Database host name.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>db_port</option> <replaceable>port</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Database port.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>db_name</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Database name.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>db_username</option> <replaceable>username</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Database username.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>db_password</option> <replaceable>password</replaceable></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Database password.</para>
					<para>Reloaded on reload signal.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Files</title>
		<para>mosquitto.conf</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Bugs</title>
		<para><command>mosquitto</command> bug information can be found at <uri
		type="webpage">http://launchpad.net/mosquitto</uri></para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>See Also</title>
		<para>
			<citerefentry>
				<refentrytitle>mosquitto</refentrytitle>
				<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
			</citerefentry>
			<citerefentry>
				<refentrytitle>mqtt</refentrytitle>
				<manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
			</citerefentry>
			<citerefentry>
				<refentrytitle>limits.conf</refentrytitle>
				<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
			</citerefentry>
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Author</title>
		<para>Roger Light <email>roger@atchoo.org</email></para>
	</refsect1>
</refentry>
